<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><mainnode><guiText>		<macTable>			<![CDATA[MAC Table]]>		</macTable>		<time>			<![CDATA[Time]]>		</time>		<preamble>			<![CDATA[Preamble]]>		</preamble>		<dstMac>			<![CDATA[Destination MAC]]>		</dstMac>		<sourceMac>			<![CDATA[Source MAC]]>		</sourceMac>		<length>			<![CDATA[Length Type]]>		</length>		<encapsulatedData>			<![CDATA[Encapsulated Data]]>		</encapsulatedData>		<endOfFrame>			<![CDATA[End of frame]]>		</endOfFrame>		<question1>			<![CDATA[1.  Where will the switch forward the frame?]]>		</question1>		<question2>			<![CDATA[2.  When the switch forwards the frame, which statement(s) are true?]]>		</question2>		<learnedCheck>			<![CDATA[Switch adds the source MAC address to the MAC table.]]>		</learnedCheck>		<broadcastCheck>			<![CDATA[Frame is a broadcast frame and will be forwarded to all ports.]]>		</broadcastCheck>		<unicastOnlyCheck>			<![CDATA[Frame is a unicast frame and will be sent to specific port only.]]>		</unicastOnlyCheck>		<unicastFloodCheck>			<![CDATA[Frame is a unicast frame and will be flooded to all ports.]]>		</unicastFloodCheck>		<unicastDropCheck>			<![CDATA[Frame is a unicast frame but it will be dropped at the switch.]]>		</unicastDropCheck>			<checkBtn>			<![CDATA[<b>Check</b>]]>		</checkBtn>		<newProblemBtn>			<![CDATA[<b>New Practice Problem</b>]]>		</newProblemBtn>		<myInputBtn>			<![CDATA[<b>Try With My Input</b>]]>		</myInputBtn>		<helpBtn>			<![CDATA[<b>Help</b>]]>		</helpBtn>		<helpTitle>			<![CDATA[Help]]>		</helpTitle>		<helpContent>			<![CDATA[This activity quizzes you on your knowledge of how a frame is forwarded on a switch.<br><br>Click the "Check" button to check your answer.<br>Click the "New Practice Problem" button to start a new computer generated practice activity.<br><br>You are given the physical topology and the MAC address table of the switch.  You are also given a frame that consists of a source and destination MAC address.<br><br>These computer generated activities will have a source and destination pair using one of the addresses shown on the topology.   Custom activities can use any desired addresses on both the MAC table and the frame.<br><br>1. Your goal is to determine how the switch will handle this frame given the MAC address table shown.<br>2. For the first question, check the port numbers to indicate where (if any) the switch will forward this frame.<br>3. For the second question, check the corresponding options to indicate how a switch will handle the frame.<br>4. Click the "Check" button to see if your answer is correct.<br><br><br>Additional Help:<br>"FF" is a broadcast MAC address and is forwarded to all ports with the exception of the origin port. <br><br>A frame is  <b>flooded</b> to all ports (except the origin) only if the switch does not have the destination MAC within the MAC table. <br><br>The switch will only add a new MAC address to the MAC table based on the source MAC address.   If the source MAC address is already in the table, nothing is added or learned.  If the source MAC address is not in the table, the address will be added.  <br><br>A switch will drop a frame if the destination and source devices are both connected to the same port and the switch has the destination MAC address in the MAC table.  In this activity, this occurs on the single port connected to the hub with 2 host devices.  <br>]]>		</helpContent>	<activityTitle>			<![CDATA[<b>Activity</b>]]>
		</activityTitle>		<scenario1>			<![CDATA[Determine how the switch forwards a frame based on the Source MAC and Destination MAC addresses and information in the switch MAC table.<br><br><b>Answer the questions below using the information provided.</b>]]>		</scenario1></guiText>	<errorMessages>		<sourceDestNotEntered>			<![CDATA[Please enter a source and destination address for the frame.<br> Destination addresses can be FF to indicate a broadcast frame.]]>		</sourceDestNotEntered>		<frameBroadcastOnly> 			<![CDATA[Incorrect. In question 2, your answer for how the switch will handle the frame based on destination address is not true.  Try again]]>		</frameBroadcastOnly> 		<frameUnicastOnly> 			<![CDATA[Incorrect. In question 2, your answer for how the switch will handle the frame based on destination address is not true.  Try again]]>		</frameUnicastOnly> 		<frameDropped> 			<![CDATA[Incorrect. In question 2, your answer for how the switch will handle the frame based on destination address is not true.  Try again]]>		</frameDropped> 		<frameDroppedSwitch> 			<![CDATA[Incorrect. In question 2, your answer for how the switch will handle the frame based on destination address is not true.  Try again]]>		</frameDroppedSwitch> 		<sourceNotInTable>				<![CDATA[Incorrect. In question 2, your answer for how  the switch will handle the source MAC address is not true.  Try again.]]>		</sourceNotInTable>		<sourceInTable>				<![CDATA[Incorrect. In question 2, your answer for how  the switch will handle the source MAC address is not true.  Try again.]]>		</sourceInTable>		<frameNotForwardedBack>			<![CDATA[Incorrect.  In question 1, the port(s) that you selected is(are) not correct.  Try again]]>		</frameNotForwardedBack>		<incorrectPortChecked>			<![CDATA[Incorrect. In question 1, the port(s) that you selected is(are) not correct. Try again.]]>		</incorrectPortChecked>		<incorrectPortNotChecked>			<![CDATA[Incorrect. In question 1, the port(s) that you selected is(are) not correct. Try again.]]>		</incorrectPortNotChecked>		<connectePortNotChecked>			<![CDATA[Incorrect. In question 1, the port(s) that you selected is(are) not correct. Try again.]]>		</connectePortNotChecked>		<inactivePortsChecked>			<![CDATA[Incorrect. In question 1, the port(s) that you selected is(are) not correct. Try again.]]>		</inactivePortsChecked>		<destPortNotChecked>			<![CDATA[Incorrect.  In question 1, the port(s) that you selected is(are) not correct.  Try again]]>		</destPortNotChecked>		<unicastFloodNotChecked>			<![CDATA[Incorrect. In question 2, your answer for how the switch will handle the frame based on destination address is not true.  Try again]]>		</unicastFloodNotChecked>		</errorMessages>	<correctMessages>		<correct1>			<![CDATA[<b>Correct! You successfully answered all questions based on the information in the frame and MAC table.</b>]]>		</correct2>		<correct2>			<![CDATA[dropped correct]]>		</correct2>		<correct3>			<![CDATA[correct broadcast]]>		</correct3>			<correct4>			<![CDATA[correct unicast]]>		</correct4>		<correct4>			<![CDATA[correct unicast flood]]>		</correct4>	</correctMessages>	 </mainnode>