<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_setup">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Use this activity to check your understanding of the main points in this chapter.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_setup2">
<text><![CDATA[<ul><li>A series of questions will be presented. This is not a quiz and your answers are not recorded.</li><li>Click <b>Answer</b> to see the answer.</li><li>Click <b>Next Question</b> to go to the next question in the series.</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="clickHere">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Click Here<br/>to Begin</b>]]></text>
</component>

<!-- Question 1 -->

<component id="ID_Q1_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Answer</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q1_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Can you mentally answer this question?<br/>Click <b>Answer</b> to see if you're correct.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q1_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[What does the Network layer do to a Transport layer PDU so that it can be communicated from host to another? ]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q1_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<p>The Network layer protocol encapsulates, or packages, the Transport layer segment or datagram so that the network can deliver it to the destination host. The IPv4 encapsulation remains in place from the time the packet leaves the Network layer of the originating host until it arrives at the Network layer of the destination host. The routing performed by intermediary devices only considers the contents of the packet header that encapsulates the segment. In all cases, the data portion of the packet—that is, the encapsulated Transport layer PDU—remains unchanged during the Network layer processes.</p>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q1_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Next<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>

<!-- Question 2 -->

<component id="ID_Q2_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Answer</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q2_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Can you mentally answer this question?<br/>Click <b>Answer</b> to see if you're correct.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q2_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[State the purpose of the Time-to-Live field in the IPv4 packet header.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q2_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<p>The Time-to-Live (TTL) field is an 8-bit binary value that indicates the remaining "life" of the packet. The TTL value is decreased by at least one each time the packet is processed by a router (that is, each hop). When the value becomes zero, the router discards or drops the packet and it is removed from the network data flow. This mechanism prevents packets that cannot reach their destination from being forwarded indefinitely between routers in a routing loop. If routing loops were permitted to continue, the network would become congested with data packets that will never reach their destination. Decrementing the TTL value at each hop ensures that it eventually becomes zero and that the packet with the expired TTL field will be dropped.
</p>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q2_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Previous<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q2_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Next<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>

<!-- Question 3 -->

<component id="ID_Q3_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Answer</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q3_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Can you mentally answer this question?<br/>Click <b>Answer</b> to see if you're correct.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q3_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[List three reasons for dividing a network into smaller groups of hosts.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q3_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<ul><li>Geographic location</li><li>Purpose</li><li>Ownership</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q3_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Previous<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q3_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Next<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>

<!-- Question 4 -->

<component id="ID_Q4_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Answer</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q4_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Can you mentally answer this question?<br/>Click <b>Answer</b> to see if you're correct.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q4_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[What are three basic characteristics of IPv4? ]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q4_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<p><b>IPv4 basic characteristics:</b></p><ul><li>Connectionless – No connection is established before sending data packets.</li><li>Best Effort (unreliable) – No overhead is used to guarantee packet delivery.</li><li>Media Independent – Operates independently of the medium carrying the data. </li></ul>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q4_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Previous<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q4_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Next<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>

<!-- Question 5 -->

<component id="ID_Q5_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Answer</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q5_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Can you mentally answer this question?<br/>Click <b>Answer</b> to see if you're correct.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q5_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[Describe the packet header field used by the router to determine where to forward a packet.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q5_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<p>The IPv4 Destination Address field contains the Layer 3 address of the destination host. The router uses the network portion of this address to determine where to forward the packet.</p>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q5_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Previous<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q5_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Next<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>

<!-- Question 6 -->

<component id="ID_Q6_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Answer</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q6_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Can you mentally answer this question?<br/>Click <b>Answer</b> to see if you're correct.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q6_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[What is the purpose of configuring a host with the address of the default gateway?]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q6_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<p>The gateway, also known as the default gateway, is needed to send a packet out of the local network. If the network portion of the destination address of the packet is different from the network of the originating host, the packet has to be routed outside the original network. To do this, the packet is sent to the gateway. This gateway is a router interface connected to the local network. The gateway interface has a Network layer address that matches the network address of the hosts. The hosts are configured to recognize that address as the gateway.</p>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q6_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Previous<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q6_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Next<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>

<!-- Question 7 -->

<component id="ID_Q7_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Answer</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q7_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Can you mentally answer this question?<br/>Click <b>Answer</b> to see if you're correct.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q7_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[What two types of networks are shown in the routing table?]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q7_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<ul><li>Directly connected networks</li><li>Remote networks</li></ul>
<p>The routing table stores information about connected and remote networks. Connected networks are directly attached to one of the router interfaces. These interfaces are the gateways for the hosts on different local networks. Remote networks are networks that are not directly connected to the router. Routes to these networks can be manually configured on the router by the network administrator or learned automatically using dynamic routing protocols.</p>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q7_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Previous<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q7_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Next<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>

<!-- Question 8 -->

<component id="ID_Q8_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Answer</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q8_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Can you mentally answer this question?<br/>Click <b>Answer</b> to see if you're correct.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q8_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[Describe the three features of a route listed in a routing table.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q8_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<p>Routes in a routing table have three main features:</p><ul><li>Destination network</li><li>Next-hop</li><li>Metric</li></ul>
<p>The router matches the destination address in the packet header with the destination network of a route in the routing table and forwards the packet to the next-hop router specified by that route. If there are two or more possible routes to the same destination, the metric is used to decide the next hop.</p>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q8_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Previous<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q8_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Next<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>

<!-- Question 9 -->

<component id="ID_Q9_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Answer</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q9_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Can you mentally answer this question?<br/>Click <b>Answer</b> to see if you're correct.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q9_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[If the destination network for a packet is not on the router's routing table, what are the two possible outcomes? ]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q9_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<p>The packet is dropped.</p><p>Or</p><p>The packet may be forwarded to the default route if one is configured</p>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q9_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Previous<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q9_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Next<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>

<!-- Question 10 -->

<component id="ID_Q10_txt01">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Answer</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q10_txt02">
<text><![CDATA[Can you mentally answer this question?<br/>Click <b>Answer</b> to see if you're correct.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q10_txt03">
<text><![CDATA[List the three possible actions a router can perform to a packet.]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q10_txt04">
<text><![CDATA[<p>Packet forwarding or routing is done packet-by-packet and hop-by-hop. Each packet is treated independently in each router along the path. At each hop, the router examines the destination IP address for each packet and then checks the routing table for forwarding information.</p>
<p>The router will do one of three things with the packet:</p><ul><li>Forward it to the next-hop router</li><li>Forward it to the destination host</li><li>Drop it</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q10_txt05">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Previous<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_Q10_txt06">
<text><![CDATA[<b>Next<br/>Question</b>]]></text>
</component>

</textcomponents>